We can consider these axioms right here, which define Peano Arithmetic,
which essentially just describe the number line. Which would be fine
if math stopped around grade 3, but if we want to
be able to describe all of math, we will need more
than just the natural numbers with addition and multiplication.
This is where set theory comes in.
Everything in math can be seen as a set, obviously numbers are
sets, but also functions are sets of pairs, graphs are sets of
points and edges and even proofs are sets of formulas.
So, if we can define what is, and what is not a valid set,
then we will have defined what is and what is not part of math.
But a set is so basic, that is hard to define. If
you try to define a set, you will likely say something like
a collection of things or a class of objects. But then, how
do you define a collection or a class? The axioms of ZFC
are a good attempt to precisely define the notion of a set.
Now, when we want to start defining the set theory, we run into
a fundamental issue with definitions. Words are defined using other words, so when
we want to define the first word, what do we do? So there
has to be some sort of a-priori assumptions, which are the axioms.
The first axiom we will look at, is the axiom of existence, which
simply asserts that there is some set. Specifically, that there is a set
with no members, the so called empty set. So at the base of
this whole set theoretic Universe, is that assumption that nothing exists.
We know that the emptyset is unique, due to
the axiom of extensionality, which just states that two
sets are equal iff they have the same members.
Once we have sets, we can define other sets, for example using
the pairing axiom, which just states that given two sets X and
Y, we can form a set with X and Y as members.
Applying this with the empty set with itself, gives us the
set containing the emptyset. So, we start with nothing, then we
can put a bag around it and so we no longer
have nothing, we have a bag with nothing in it.
This is obviously pretty dumb, but we are essentially defining
the natural numbers. The emptyset is 0, the set containing
the empty set is 1, and then from here, just
like Russian Dolls, we will define the successor to be
the set of all predecessors. Which requires the union axiom
So, we can define 2 as the set containing 0 and
1. Then 3 as the set with 0,1 and 2. Then
we can continue this indefinitely, resulting in the ordinal numbers.
The ordinals, which are essentially just the natural numbers, will form the spine
of the set theoretic Universe. We will use the following axiom, known as
the power set axiom to define the rest of the sets